Mss.B.L563
American Philosophical Society
I. Michael (Isadore Michael) Lerner papers, ca. 1930s-1970s
Circa 1930s-1970s
Mss.B.L563
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet Ca. 2500 items
The correspondence in this collection concerns behavior genetics, evolution, heredity, etc. There is material relating to the congresses of the Permanent International Committee on Genetics, and the IXth (Bellagio, 1953), Xth (Montreal, 1958), and XIth (The Hague, 1963) International Congress of Genetics. There is also correspondence pertaining to the Cold Spring Harbor Symposium on Quantitative Biology (1955), the Mendel Semi-Centennial Symposium (1950), the Soviet geneticists' visit to the U.S. in 1967, and to Anton R. Zhebrak.
Ca. 2500 items.
Lerner, I. Michael(Isadore Michael),1910-
Box 1-6
Scope and Contents note
In Lerner's correspondence there is a fair amount of exchange with Russian geneticists, nearly all of it after 1960. He corresponded much with Ernst Mayr. His esteem for Richard Goldschmidt was not lessened by his firm disagreement with Goldschmidt's radical ideas of an abrupt origin of new species by single mega-mutations. There is little correspondence to reflect Lerner's great debt to his colleague Everett Dempster, whose mastery of mathematical methods led Lerner deeper into the analysis of population genetics. There is, however, a considerable volume of items stemming from Lerner's long and very responsible activity in organizing the International Congresses of Genetics from 1953 through 1963; as well as the Cold Spring Harbor Symposium of 1955, the Mendel Semicentennial of 1950, a visit by Soviet geneticists to the United States in 1967, and the like.
Includes correspondence, minutes of committee meetings, manuscript of translation of Medvedev's book on Lysenko, etc. About 2500 items, in 12 boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Dr. Isadore Michael Lerner, 1971-1977.
Biographical/Historical note
Isadore Michael Lerner was a geneticist.
Lerner's parentage made Russian his native language, but his command of English was superb. He spoke with little or no accent, his knowledge of idioms was excellent, and his written style, like that of another compatriot, Theodosius Dobzhansky, was marked by clarity and good syntax. He came to North America in 1927, a penniless refugee seeking a university education. By good luck, for it was the time of the Great Depression, he found a job digging ditches and watering chickens in the poultry farm of the University of British Columbia. Learning that in order to hold that job indefinitely he would have to pursue a major in poultry husbandry at the university, he entered upon a career in science almost fortuitously. After obtaining his bachelor's degree, he embarked upon graduate study, after being much encouraged by an interview with Theodosius Dobzhansky, who was visiting the university and whose enthusiasm and friendly advice made a great impression upon the young graduate student.
After obtaining his master's degree at the University of British Columbia in 1932, Lerner was told that financial stringency was forcing the university to eliminate his position. Fortunately for science, he obtained support for further graduate study at the University of California, Berkeley, in poultry husbandry. Upon receiving his Ph.D. degree, in 1936, Lerner was at once given a faculty position. He then moved up the academic ladder to the rank of professor, continuing for 22 years. In 1958, after the acclaim that met the publication of his first three books, he shifted to the Department of Genetics as its chairman. In 1963 he resigned that office, and ten years later became professor emeritus. During his last thirty years Lerner was plagued with much ill health. He underwent several abdominal operations and developed cataracts on both eyes, which were also operated on. Eventually he had a detached retina that greatly impaired his eyesight. In all these difficulties he was greatly assisted by his wife, Ruth Stuart, who had been a fellow student at the University of British Columbia and was a trained scientist herself. She was Lerner's eyes and ears in those last decades, and helped to produce the new editions of his books.
Lerner's career fell into three somewhat overlapping periods. During the first, he made fundamental contributions to poultry genetics and improvement. A majority of his published papers stem from that time. He first worked on the genetics of relative growth and disease resistance; then on components of egg production; the effects of selection in conjunction with inbreeding; empirical tests of theoretical predictions of gains from the simultaneous selection of several different characteristics; and the derivation of an "optimum selection index" that received wide attention and use and led to a doubling of egg production in commercial flocks.
The second period may be dated from the beginnings of his preparation for his acknowledged masterpiece, Genetic Homeostasis, a very important contribution to genetic theory. It embodies the idea that the most adapted type within a population is not one simply conforming to a phenotypic norm, but one whose development and reproductive life history adjust to the varying environment in such manner as to preserve high fitness. Correspondingly, the most successful population is one that can successfully meet the challenge of long-range environmental changes. Homeostatic devices that stabilize an individual's reproductive performance have high selective value; the population benefits from having a heterogeneous genetic composition even beneath an apparently uniform phenotype. Thus Lerner emphasized the very great importance in evolution of "buffered and balanced genotypes, integrated genepools, and coadaptation."
In Lerner's final period he attempted to introduce these evolutionary concepts into his teaching and social thinking. His superb textbook, Heredity, Evolution and Society, written after Curt Stern had joined the Berkeley faculty and become his friend, exemplified Lerner's cautious, critical attitude toward the extension of scientific evolutionary theory into human affairs. He was neither an extreme sociobiologist nor a virulent opponent of such ideas. He treated the most controversial subjects, such as the inheritance of intelligence, natural selection in human populations, and the nature of human races, with restraint, willingness to face facts and to admit ignorance. His breadth of knowledge in fields outside his specialties was extraordinary. In a single paper, for example, he quoted aptly from Isaiah Berlin, William Blake, Michelangelo, Samuel Butler, Bertrand Russell, Francis Bacon, Aristotle, and Bergson.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Astaurov, Boris L. Correspondence (12 items) 1961-1973
Belyaev, Dmitri K. Correspondence (15 items) 1964-1971
Cold Spring Harbor Symposium Correspondence (56 items) 1954-1955
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (280 items) 1931-1975
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Correspondence (21 items) 1962-1972
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict Correspondence (27 items) 1947-1955
Lush, Jay L. Correspondence (30 items) 1942-1948
Mather, Kenneth Correspondence (34 items) 1948-1971
Mayr, Ernst Correspondence (45 items) 1952-1975
Medvedev, Zhores A. Manuscripts (3 boxes) 1962-1975
Mendel Semicentennial Symposium Correspondence (32 items) 1950-1952
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (12 items) 1959-1964
Needham, Joseph Correspondence (16 items) 1939-1951
Permanent International Committee on Genetic Congresses Records (356 items) 1952-1961
Waddington, Conrad Hal Correspondence (22 items) 1946-1962
Wallace, Bruce Correspondence (22 items) 1952-1958
Wright, Sewall Correspondence (11 items) 1935-1949
Zhebrak, Anton Ramanavich Correspondence (26 items) 1945-1946
Custodial History note
This collection previously had the longer call number: Mss.B.L563, L995m.L1. The call number was sortented to Mss.B.L563 May, 2012.
Berg, Raisa, 1913-; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict, 1878-1958; Gustafsson, Åke, -- 1908-; Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964; Landauer, Walter, 1896-; Lewontin, Richard Charles, 1929-; Lush, Jay L., (Jay Laurence); Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich, 1898-1976; Mather, Kenneth; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005; Medawar, P. B. (Peter Brian), 1915-; Medvedev, Zhores A., 1925-; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Needham, Joseph, 1900-; Neel, James V., (James Van Gundia), 1915-2000; Permanent International Committee on Genetics.; Sonneborn, T.M., (Tracy Morton), 1905-1981; Timofeev-Resovskiĭ, N. V., (Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich), 1900-1981; Waddington, C. H., (Conrad Hal), 1905-1975; Wallace, Bruce, 1920-; Wright, Sewall, 1889-1988; Zhebrak, Anton R.; Behavior genetics.; Biology.; Evolution.; Galley proofs.; Genetics.; Heredity.; Manuscripts (for publication).
- Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide
  - Astaurov, Boris L., 1961-1973; Correspondence ( 12 items )
    Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks; Drosophila genetics; Koltsov, N. K.; Publication
  - Belyaev, Dmitri K., 1964-1971; Correspondence ( 15 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Educational matters -- U.S.S.R.; Publication; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Cold Spring Harbor Symposium, 1954-1955; Correspondence ( 56 items )
    Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Population genetics
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1931-1975; Correspondence ( 280 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Crow, James F.; Drosophila genetics; Editorial matters; Genetics -- Homeostasis; Honors -- Nobel Prize; Human genetics -- Race; International Congress of Genetics -- Twelfth Congress; Memorabilia; Muller, Hermann Joseph; National Academy of Sciences; Philosophy of science; Population genetics; Publication; Reviews; Russian politics and science -- Dubinin, Nikolai Petrovich; Russian politics and science -- Lobashov, M. E.; Russian politics and science -- Medvedev, Zhores A.; Russian politics and science -- Timofeeff- Ressovsky, Nikolai W.; Russian politics and science -- Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Wallace, Bruce; World War II -- Impact on science
  - Dunn, Leslie Clarence, 1962-1972; Correspondence ( 21 items )
    American Philosophical Society; Biographical and personal data; Provine, William B.; Publication; Russian politics and science
  - Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict, 1947-1955; Correspondence ( 27 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Drosophila genetics; Educational matters; Evolution; Genetics; Publication; Reviews; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
  - Lush, Jay L., 1942-1948; Correspondence ( 30 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Mouse genetics; Population genetics; Poultry genetics; Publication
  - Mather, Kenneth, 1948-1971; Correspondence ( 34 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Educational matters; Genetics; Genetics of plants; Poultry genetics; Teaching
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1952-1975; Correspondence ( 45 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Genetics; History of biology, especially genetics; Publication; Reviews; Russian politics and science; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Medvedev, Zhores A., 1962-1975; Manuscripts ( 3 boxes )
    Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Solzhenitsyn, Alexandr; Timofeeff-Ressovsky, Nikolai W.; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc. -- Medvedev, Zhores A.
  - Mendel Semicentennial Symposium, 1950-1952; Correspondence ( 32 items )
    Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Mendel, Gregor; Publication
  - Muller, Hermann Joseph, 1959-1964; Correspondence ( 12 items )
    Population genetics; Publication; Russian politics and science
  - Needham, Joseph, 1939-1951; Correspondence ( 16 items )
    Academic freedom; Biographical and personal data; Physiology; Publication; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; World War II -- Impact on science
  - Permanent International Committee on Genetic Congresses, 1952-1961; Records ( 356 items )
    Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Genetics -- Nomenclature; International Congress of Genetics -- Eleven Congress; International Congress of Genetics -- Ninth Congress; International Congress of Genetics -- Tenth Congress; International Congress of Human Genetics -- First Congress; International Congress of Zoology -- Sixteenth Congress; International Union of Biological Societies; Permanent International Committee on Genetic Congresses -- Constitution; Permanent International Committee on Genetic Congresses -- Minutes; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Waddington, Conrad Hal, 1946-1962; Correspondence ( 22 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Genetics; Publication; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1952-1958; Correspondence ( 22 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Political issues; Population genetics; Poultry genetics; Reviews; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
  - Wright, Sewall, 1935-1949; Correspondence ( 11 items )
    Poultry genetics; Referee's report; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
  - Zhebrak, Anton Ramanavich, 1945-1946; Correspondence ( 26 items )
    Committee activities; Publication; Russian politics and science; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; World War II -- Impact on science
- Photographs, 25.0 Photograph(s)
  Scope and Contents note
  A selection of photographs from the I. Michael (Isadore Michael) Lerner papers.
  - Bruce Wallace and Hampton Carson, Pavia, 1953., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Wallace and Carson standing outside of building, holding bottles.
  - Dobzhansky and students at the XI International Congress of Genetics, The Hague, 1963., 1.0 Photograph(s); Eighteen men and one woman standing on steps outside of building.
  - Epling and Buzzati-Traverso, Pavia, 1953., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of two men, standing outside, columns in background.
  - Epling, Falconer and Roberson, Pavia, 1953, 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of three men standing outside.
  - G. Teissier and M. J. Sirks, Tokyo, 1956., 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length view of Teissier and Sirks, seated, with glasses.
  - Herman Muller with unidentified group of scientists., n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Informal, black and white photograph taken in a laboratory.
  - I. M. Learner and Prince Yoshinomiya [?] at Matsushima Hotel, Sendai, Japan, 1956., 1.0 Photograph(s); Lerner and Yoshinomiya seated in hotel room.
  - I. M. Lerner and Marcus Roades, seated, holding papers, Tokyo, 1956., 1.0 Photograph(s); Lerner and Roads, wearing glasses, seated looking at papers, people in background.
  - I. M. Lerner and Mather, Pavia, 1953., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full view of Lerner and Mather standing outside, in conversation.
  - I. M. Lerner and Ruggiero Ceppelini, San Francisco, 1954., 1.0 Photograph(s); Lerner and Ceppelini standing outside near water, bridge construction in background.
  - J. L. Lush, Reeve, Forbes and Roberson, Cold Spring Harbor, 1955, 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length view of three men standing outside, building in background, other people half out of frame.
  - Kenneth Mather and John M. Thoday, Cold Spring Harbor, 1955, 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Mather and Thoday standing outside, house in background.
  - Lerner holding chicken, Okayama, 1956., 1.0 Photograph(s); Lerner, standing with group of unidentified men, holding a chicken.
  - Lerner, Tanaka, Komai and eight unidentified men standing outside., 1956; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length group portrait of eleven men standing outside building.
  - Medvedev and V. P. Efroimson, seated., 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length view of two men sitting.
  - Medvedev with woman and two young men [family?], seated on bench., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of four people on bench, trees in background.
  - N. P. Dubinin and H. H. Plough, Academy of Sciences, Institute of Biophysics, 1958., 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 length view of two men, standing outside in front of building.
  - N. Vavilov, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of Vavilov, bust.
  - R. Cleland, R. Levine and Waddington, Tokyo, 1956, 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length view of men standing outside, people and building in background.
  - Sergi Sergeevich Tsechetverikoff, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait, bust length, of Tsechetverikoff.
  - T. Dobzhansky, Dempster, I. M. Lerner, Natalia Dobzansky and an unidientified man, seated at table., 1.0 Photograph(s); Five people seated at table, people in background.
  - Z. A. Medvedev, seated at desk near photograph of his father, A. Medvedev., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Z. Medvedev seated, reading a book, book shelves in background, picture of A. Medvedev on wall.
  - Z. Medvedev with twin brother, Roy Medvedev., 1970; 1.0 Photograph(s); Bust length group portrait of Z. and Roy Medvedev.
  - Zhores Aleksandrovich Medvedev, formal portrait., 1970; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait, bust length, of Z. Medvedev.
  - Zhukousky [?], half length, profile, seated with graduate students, Zhores Medvedev, Tat'iana Alekseevna Maurina, and Vladimir Evgen'evich Egorov half length standing., 1.0 Photograph(s); Informal, black and white photograph taken in a laboratory.